<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content"><channel><title>Tom Twardzik</title><description>Writer. Content Marketer. SEO.</description><link>tomtwardzik.com</link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 20:36:20 -0400</lastBuildDate><pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 20:36:20 -0400</pubDate><ttl>250</ttl><atom:link href="tomtwardzik.com/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><guid isPermaLink="true">tomtwardzik.com/blog/remove-media-shortcut</guid><title>Remove Ugly Web Media with Shortcuts and JavaScript</title><description>Wield the power of iOS Shortcuts and a bit of JavaScript to clear webpages of unpleasant photos and videos while you read and research.</description><link>tomtwardzik.com/blog/remove-media-shortcut</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 12:00:00 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>Remove Ugly Web Media with Shortcuts and JavaScript</h1><img src="tomtwardzik.com/assets/ipad-on-desk.jpg" alt="iPad and Apple Pencil lying on desk."/><p><em>Image: <a href="https://unsplash.com/@aoirostudio">Francois Hoang</a></em></p><p><em>How a little JavaScript and a Shortcut let me remove ugly images/distracting videos from web pages while I’m working and researching.</em></p><p>Freelance writers have to be adventurous, un-picky, ready to learn about a new subject every week. You research hard about your client's topic, throw yourself into it until you're more than a surface-level summarizer, then enjoy that best kind of learning where you <em>become</em> the teacher, exploring the subject in your own words and absorbing it further into your bones.</p><p>It's a thrilling career and one that pays off in more ways than a check. Knowledge, new perspectives and a deeper understanding of special and specialized parts of the world in which we live come to freelance writers.</p><p>Sometimes, though, the topics aren't exactly <em>pleasant</em>. And research into these topics (think health topics, pest control, toilet repair) often surfaces less-than-pretty pictures and videos.</p><p>These can be… distracting while I'm trying to write.</p><p>And don't forget about those auto-playing pop-up videos that some websites splash onto every page!</p><p>Let's get rid of 'em.</p><p><strong>Tl;dr - <a href="https://www.icloud.com/shortcuts/c68e71a5ccf74cf589859630904bd2b8">Download the shortcut here</a>!</strong></p><h2>Hide Ugly Media with Shortcuts on iOS</h2><p>To make these dirty jobs a little easier on the eyes and a little less distracting from the flow, I created a <strong>simple shortcut</strong>.</p><p>I write mostly on my iPad, so this trick uses the Shortcuts app and its ability to run JavaScript on a web page in Safari.</p><blockquote><p>If you're using a Mac, <a href="tomtwardzik.com/blog/remove-media-bookmarklet">check out my bookmarklet</a> that does the same thing!</p></blockquote><p>When I'm reading a page that contains an ugly picture or a nonsense video, I can tap the share button, choose my shortcut from the list of actions and watch the media magically disappear.</p><h2>The Code</h2><p><em>A little coding know-how goes a long way.</em></p><p>I'm a beginner iOS programmer, an amateur web developer and a copy-and-paste JavaScript coder. Turns out, that's enough to get a good bit done on a computer!</p><p>To write the JavaScript code that runs in this shortcut, I adapted some JS from a <a href="https://www.icloud.com/shortcuts/46cc38e259324f7494e4c66829007edc">Shortcut</a> that was <a href="https://twitter.com/livbem/status/1223043752878460928?s=20">created by an engineer on Apple's Safari team</a> to get a web page's canonical URL instead of its AMP address.</p><p>I only had to modify, not <em>write from scratch</em>, a few lines of JS—familiarity is enough to figure out what's going on in the function and Google your way to the proper substitutions.</p><h2>The Shortcut</h2><p>It uses only 1 action:</p><ol><li><strong>Run JavaScript on Web Page</strong></li></ol><p>Add that action by searching for it in the actions panel.</p><p>Then, replace the boilerplate JavaScript with this:</p><pre><code>var images = document.getElementsByTagName('img');
for (i = 0; i &lt; images.length; i++) {
    images[i].style.display = "none";
}

var vids = document.getElementsByTagName('video');
for (i = 0; i &lt; vids.length; i++) {
    vids[i].style.display = "none";
}

completion(true);
</code></pre><p>First, the code finds all instances of <code>&lt;img&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;video&gt;</code> HTML tags.</p><p>Then, it loops over both sets, changing each element's display property to "none". That removes them from the page.</p><p>(If you're better at JS than me, feel free to improve this code!)</p><img src="tomtwardzik.com/assets/shortcuts-js-action-screenshot.png" alt="Screenshot of Shortcuts "Run JavaScript on web page" action."/><p><em>This is the single action used in this shortcut.</em></p><h3>Configuring the Shortcut to Run on Web Pages</h3><p>To use the shortcut from the share sheet in Safari on iOS, tap the "…" button next to its name at the top of the editor and turn on "Show in Share Sheet".</p><p>Tap "Share Sheet Types", tap "Deselect All" and, finally, select only "Safari web pages".</p><p>You should also rename the shortcut. Mine's called "Remove Media from Web Page". Give it a nice color and a recognizable glyph, too!</p><p>Now, back in the main editor, tap and hold on the blue placeholder text "Web Page" right at the top of the action. From the menu that appears, select <strong>Shortcut Input</strong>.</p><p>That sets the input to the website you'll pass into the shortcut from the share sheet.</p><p><strong>Now, test it!</strong></p><img src="tomtwardzik.com/assets/share-sheet-screenshot.png" alt="Screenshot of share sheet shortcuts"/><p><em>Before (left) and after running the shortcut.</em></p><p>Go to a page in Safari that has an image or video, tap the <strong>Share</strong> button, scroll down until you see the name of the shortcut you've just created and run it!</p><p>You'll have to allow Shortcuts to run JavaScript on the webpage. Once you tap "Allow" the unwanted media will... poof—disappear!</p><p><strong>Download the shortcut <a href="https://www.icloud.com/shortcuts/c68e71a5ccf74cf589859630904bd2b8">here</a>!</strong></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">tomtwardzik.com/blog/a-more-readable-internet</guid><title>A More Readable Internet</title><description>My goal: make my site readable to anyone curious enough to inspect its source code—like the old days. Things have not turned out to be as simple as I'd hoped.</description><link>tomtwardzik.com/blog/a-more-readable-internet</link><pubDate>Mon, 9 Dec 2019 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>A More Readable Internet</h1><img src="tomtwardzik.com/assets/html-source-code-screenshot.JPG" alt="Messi pointing toward the sky in celebration."/><p>I built this website using words. I set a goal: make my site readable to the people who are curious enough to inspect its source code. I think I succeeded. But things have not turned out to be as simple as I'd hoped.</p><h2>The Complicated Web</h2><p>One part of working in SEO is knowing how to analyze and repair the foundations of struggling websites. For a large e-commerce site with thousands of pages, that task can be as difficult as repairing the physical foundation of a sprawling brick-and-mortar supermarket. Bug fixes and style revisions and new initiatives cause rapid expansion—the kind that can leave wires tangled and cause problems later on when further expansion is required.</p><p>That on-the-fly expansion is hard to avoid. You can't anticipate everything when you begin writing your site. This, though, is the reason for the impenetrable wall of <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> tags and lines of CSS that often greets explorers who inspect the source of a webpage. That's not readable.</p><h2>My Goal</h2><p>I wanted my website to be as readable as possible when a visitor presses ⌘ + alt + U in their browser. I wanted them to see a neatly organized, easily recognizable poem of <code>&lt;h1&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;h2&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;p&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;img&gt;</code> tags.</p><p>My goal was zero Javascript. Nothing but static HTML and CSS styling pulled from a separate, carefully organized file. (In this, I've succeeded.)</p><p>But I had to make the site responsive to screen size. So I added a couple of classes—<code>.desktop</code> and <code>.mobile</code> and sprinkled them all over the place. Though it worked, this off-the-cuff formatting quickly complicated my code. I decided to rebuild almost entirely, just a month after I'd set the site live.</p><p>A week and a half later, the site was rebuilt and beautifully organized. I felt clever and successful. I was ready to implement dark mode.</p><p>That, I discovered, is more difficult than simply duplicating every color property and adding a second version for <code>@media (prefers-color-scheme: dark)</code>. Or, rather, it is exactly that difficult. Because that process is more than tedious: it's convoluted and inefficient and messy.</p><p>It was time to suck up my pride and abandon my goal of writing a website that looked like it had been <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19991117024224/http://apple.com/">built in 1999</a>.</p><p>I added CSS variables.</p><h2>Variables Are for Programmers</h2><p>CSS variables are technically called <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/Using_CSS_custom_properties">custom properties</a>. They work like this: you define a variable for a specific property. I used a few (shown below) to store dark and light versions of the colors in my theme.</p><pre><code>     :root {
        --color-background-body: #f2f2f7;  
        --color-background-main: #ffffff;
        --color-text-default: #1c1c1e;
    }

    @media (prefers-color-scheme: dark) {
      :root {
        --color-background-body: #000000;
        --color-background-main: #1c1c1e;
        --color-text-default: #ffffff
      }
    }
</code></pre><p>I looked at what I'd done and felt… conflicted.</p><p>Would a regular (non-technical) visitor be happy to open my site's source code and see a list of variables? Would I, just a year ago, have understood what I was looking at?</p><p>Few. And not immediately.</p><p>But as far as I can tell, this is the simplest way of achieving the responsiveness that modern websites <em>must</em> prioritize. In fact, variables are much more readable than a sheet specifying the full hex values for every element of the site. That turns a CSS file into a cascade of <strong>#ff9500</strong> and <strong>rgb(155,220,255)</strong>.</p><h2>A Little Learning or a Lot of Nonsense</h2><p>CSS variables are not immediately readable for every person. But neither is HTML, in general. But upon closer inspection, you can get a general idea of what's happening with both. A custom property called <code>--color-text-default</code> is as semantically informative as an <code>&lt;article&gt;</code> or <code>&lt;table&gt;</code> tag.</p><p>Where a sheet of hex numbers reads like a coded message, a list of variables reads like a glossary of terms placed at the beginning of the text. It makes reading everything that follows easier.</p><p>Of course, CSS custom properties are not a solution to the problems faced by enormous websites. But the principles behind these variables—efficiency and organization—are important for sites of every size. Whether you're a small business whose website is maintained by one or two employees or an individual doing it yourself, CSS variables can make maintenance, revisions and expansions much easier.</p><h2>Nothing to Hide</h2><p>You <em>can</em> build a modern website with simple, semantic code. It's a great way to be more transparent to users and make the jobs of future developers (and you) easier.</p><p>It's up to web developers to write with care and discipline. Developers: be the poets of the web, efficient and strict with syntax. Be the woodworkers who proudly brand their initials on the well-built frame of an upholstered chair. Few will see them. But those who do pull back the fabric to reveal the wood beneath will appreciate your craftsmanship.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">tomtwardzik.com/blog/on-writing-simply</guid><title>On Writing Simply</title><description>That old quote about writing being as simple as sitting over a typewriter to bleed? That's plain text. No fuss, just the work.</description><link>tomtwardzik.com/blog/on-writing-simply</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2019 12:00:00 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>On Writing Simply</h1><img src="tomtwardzik.com/assets/green-used-remington-typewriter.JPG" alt="Green Remington typewriter with black keys."/><p>I wrote this piece on a combination of 1) a MacBook Pro (late–2012) and 2) an iPad Pro (3rd Gen) using a combination of:</p><ol><li><a href="https://helloedit.raphaelkabo.com/">HelloEdit</a></li><li><a href="ia.net">iA Writer</a></li><li>Apple Notes</li><li>and more…</li></ol><p>I discovered HelloEdit via a post on <a href="https://512pixels.net">512pixels.net</a>, the very site which, it turns out, <a href="https://512pixels.net/2011/05/markdown-new-word51/">inspired the creation of this tool</a> with an article eight years ago. <span class="fn" id="1"><a href="#1-f">1</a></span></p><p>I’ve never used Word 5.1 or AppleWorks. The earliest memory of writing I have is on the family’s blue iMac when I was five or six or seven.</p><p>I must have been using the Microsoft Word of the early 2000s or an equivalent program–I remember its overwhelming (to a six-year-old) toolset, its rows of toolbars and tiny icons–because the thing that sticks with this memory is that I printed the story out on one piece of paper, front and back, in landscape orientation.</p><p>And I printed it in blue font.</p><p>I have no idea why, any of this. I also manually shaped the text on the page (using the Return key–the only way I knew how) to leave the bottom-right quarter of the page blank. In that space, I hand-illustrated the story’s first scene with crayons.</p><p>That was my first published work.</p><p>Discovering HelloEdit and reading about the simple origins of text-editing to which it pays homage has led me to realize something, in retrospect. I had never understood plain text writing until I started writing on an iPad.</p><h2>Plain Text</h2><blockquote><p>“They [word processors] started trying to help—and helping a writer while he or she is writing is impossible.” <span class="fn" id="2"><a href="#2-f">2</a></span></p></blockquote><p>I suppose TextEdit and Notepad and Apple Notes and the deceased <a href="https://433labs.com/">Plain Text</a> on iOS were my first experiences with pure-text editing. However, the revelation came when I downloaded <a href="ia.net">iA Writer</a> on my iPad. That was when I discovered Markdown.</p><p>I’d read Daring Fireball through its RSS feed but I’d never visited the website long enough to notice John Gruber’s Markdown project. It’s the gilding for the kind of plain text writing I’d been doing in short bursts in the Notes app or TextEdit, rendered with simple, clear formatting.</p><p>Markdown is the cure for my incessant urge to format and reformat text more than I write it. It’s incredibly productive. And I enjoy the uniform beauty of watching my progress as I build a sturdy stack of paragraph blocks. Markdown makes plain text beautiful, which makes writing at length in plain text truly pleasant.</p><p>I’ve grown to like using fixed-width fonts (to which I was <a href="https://ia.net/writer/blog/a-typographic-christmas">turned on by iA Writer, mainly</a>), especially. <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/a-writers-justification">Full justification is ugly</a>. But rectangular chunks of fixed-width text make me feel accomplished—like I’ve stacked heavy weights at the gym or built a physical object with tools and sweat.</p><p>That old quote about writing being as simple as sitting over a typewriter to bleed? Writing in a word processor feels more like sitting down at a table scattered with various styles of paper, pens, pencils and erasers and having to sort through it all to choose the right combination.</p><p>Plain text writing, on the other hand, feels like an empty desk with a pen and a notebook. Or a manual typewriter. Instead of clicking past a template selection window to tinker with line spacing and the right serif or sans-serif font, I can <em>get to work</em>.</p><p>A word processor is called a word <em>processor</em>, after all. It’s better as a tool for <em>processing</em> text: editing, formatting, exporting, publishing.</p><p>Plain text is the writing tool.</p><p>And as a place for writing, it’s less intimidating than a document in a word processor, too. There, you’re faced with a blank page, that imposing monolithic wall in your face. That romanticized foe. Maybe it’s allowed too much power, but it has an effect on me like an unfamiliar darkness. Even with the knowledge that scary movies are just movies and that ghosts aren’t real, the right combination of sleeplessness, cloud cover and unknown noises can put the hairs up on the back of my neck and quicken my breath.</p><p>The fixed blank page is intimidating. It has a length and width and it begins empty, a sign of the work ahead.</p><p>Whereas the plain text editor is an empty creative space without size or shape. A TextEdit window is infinitely resizable and adapts without argument to different window shapes. It’s an endless scroll that doesn’t <em>expect</em> any amount of work. It allows you to write your thoughts with as much concision or flourish as you want, and then export without judgment.</p><p>If I’m exporting plain text to a page-based format, I’m often surprised by the number of pages I’ve written. But regardless of its final form, I feel satisfied knowing that the text I’ve written is just as long as it needs to be.</p><h2>Countless</h2><p>School writing, you’ll probably remember, is all about the page count. <span class="fn" id="3"><a href="#3-f">3</a></span> Your brain in high school:</p><blockquote><p>Keep those paragraphs trim and cut them at the very start of the fourth or fifth line of each one to get the most out of the next paragraph’s line break–more white space equals fewer words and fewer words equal less work. Don’t break a paragraph too close to the bottom of the page or that pesky word processor will bend the rules and fit it all into the margin.</p></blockquote><p>But <em>writing</em> writing–it’s not about page count. It’s not about counting at all. Writing is about saying what you need to say in the way that best says it. Regardless of length, shape or line height. Plain text lets you do the essential writing with the bare minimum “help”.</p><p>It also gives you the flexibility to continue the work elsewhere, when a more complex or specific environment suits it. Plain text is the tool that you can take with you anywhere.</p><p>iA Writer and other plain text editors–the incredible <a href="https://getdrafts.com/">Drafts</a>, for example–provide powerful exporting options. These apps recognize that they are, by definition, merely the starting places for the work. When the writing is finished, the words move on to their destinations: to word processors, to email clients, to HTML files.</p><p>The great achievement of the writer is to have written. No matter the allure of publication or recognition, the writer’s ultimate triumph and highest joy comes from the completion of the writing. When it is finished, it is finished. The word processor blinks at an unfortunate, oddly-shaped, two-fifths full final page. The plain text editor does not judge but presents the completed structure of words, ready for what’s next.</p><hr><ol><li><span id="1-f"></span>HelloEdit revealed itself to me at just the right time: my job had recently "upgraded" me from my personal MacBook Pro to a one-year-newer company MBP that had none of my well-oiled workflows or favorite apps. (But it has that extra click in the trackpad for whatever that’s for!) // Suddenly, instead of writing in iA Writer and exporting, I had Word 2011 (2011!). That’s a good way to kill a writer’s productivity for a few days while they search for alternatives. So I’m quite thankful for HelloEdit’s perfect simplicity and that I don’t have to download anything or sign up to use it. <a href="#1">⤴️</a></li></ol><ol start="2"><li><span id="2-f"></span><a href="https://512pixels.net/2011/05/markdown-new-word51/">https://512pixels.net/2011/05/markdown-new-word51/</a> <a href="#2">⤴️</a></li></ol><ol start="3"><li><span id="3-f"></span>Page counts are an artifact of the past, like word counts for print magazines or writing a “column”. Teachers, please: we understand the need for some kind of metric that requires reluctant students to write more than a few sentences. But do the right thing and teach students to expand their pieces by asking more questions, not by fluffing up the easy answers. (Teaching is difficult, and teachers are due much respect. But for much of my childhood, even the good English teachers failed to teach most of us to write more by engaging more deeply with the subject.) <a href="#3">⤴️</a></li></ol>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">tomtwardzik.com/blog/messi</guid><title>#10: For the Love of Football</title><description>On the joy of watching something utterly new from the foot of the greatest player in the world.</description><link>tomtwardzik.com/blog/messi</link><pubDate>Fri, 6 Sep 2019 12:00:00 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>#10: For the Love of Football</h1><img src="tomtwardzik.com/assets/messi_hands_up_celebration.jpeg" alt="Messi pointing toward the sky in celebration."/><p>Soccer was my favorite sport when I was young—elementary school age. I used to see it on TV as I browsed through channels and would watch a few minutes of those little men running across an enormous field of grass. I played in the local youth league but that was nothing like what I saw on TV. I could <em>see</em> the edges of the field on which I played. I was fast at that age and that was more important than any kind of skill on the ball. I loved playing soccer and I was pretty good.</p><p>I maintained to anyone who asked, however, that soccer was my favorite sport to <em>play</em> while football—NFL football—was my favorite sport to <em>watch</em>.</p><p>I also thought that, like every other major sport I followed, the U.S. league was the league to watch (oh naiveté). I thought that the MLS was like the NFL, the NBA, the MLB—the center of the sport, the league everybody else was already watching and the one with all of the biggest stars (<em>This Freddy Adu guy everyone’s talking about—he must be the best in the world!</em> <span class="fn" id="1"><a href="#1-f">1</a></span>)</p><p>Maybe that’s why I didn’t watch much soccer, even though I loved playing it.</p><p>I didn’t get it, then. I wasn’t interested in the world outside my neighborhood when I was eight. And no one set me straight because no one I knew was watching international soccer.</p><p>But I get it now. And I’m lucky that I got started when I did, too. Luckier than I could have known as an eight-year-old.</p><h2>May 1, 2005</h2><p>I’m excited for the end of the school year and summer. I’m a stupid kid. I have no idea that, across the Atlantic, a kid only seven years older than me is <a href="https://www.goal.com/en/news/messi-nets-stunning-free-kick-for-600th-barcelona-goal/gnaupjmogdp11af1sge2qk31k">scoring his first goal</a> for the Barcelona senior team.</p><p>Lionel Messi has arrived.</p><h2>May 1, 2019</h2><p>I’m sitting at my desk at a marketing agency in Manhattan, listening to the commentary as Barcelona lead Liverpool 1–0 in the Champions League semifinal at Camp Nou. The game is hidden behind other work-related windows on my screen, streaming from Spain to space to a tiny window in the corner of my computer.</p><p>I’ve gotten pretty good at working while listening for the ebb and flow of the crowd noise and the changing inflections of the commentators’ voices. I usually know when to pop the game window to the front to watch for a few seconds as an attack builds before I get back to work. I’ve seen many goals this way: crowd noise rising, that sudden edge in a commentator’s voice as he says “Here comes [insert player] down the sideline, crossing it innnnnnn…”</p><p>This time, though, I missed it.</p><p>There was no buildup to hear. No excited commentators; they were fooled, too. The teams had lined up for a set piece from too far away. It was crossing distance, not shooting distance. The commentators waited calmly and the crowd quieted with anticipation.</p><p>So as it happened in real time, I didn’t notice. The words didn’t register as the kick-taker placed the ball down and the wall lined up. The stadium waited. The commentary team kept chatting. I kept working.</p><p>In my ears, it went from quiet set-piece anticipation to thunder from the stands and the commentator shouting, “Oh my goodness! OHHH my goodness!”</p><p>I snapped to the window and saw Messi sitting on the grass pumping his arms and absorbing the shocked, struck-by-lightning energy from the crowd. Tens of thousands of people wearing both teams' colors had their arms over their heads, literally bowing down to him.</p><p>It was goal <a href="https://twitter.com/OptaJose/status/1123691683621818373">600</a>.</p><h2>Feelings</h2><p>I’m jittery as I write this, feeling that strange kind of adrenaline that even televised sports manage to produce.</p><p>I’m thinking, I haven’t even watched soccer for that long. I don’t know the legends or buy into the superstitions. A bit more than two seasons, maybe, of seriously following the sport. (There was that ’14 World Cup, too, and the brief hype around the USMNT. Ha. So long ago…)</p><p>I’m a skeptical person. I don’t trust hype, usually.</p><p>But soccer gives me a feeling, gets my heart going like few other things. And I like to think that bandwagon-jumping is inapplicable when the greatest player in the history of the sport. I’d still begrudge a friend suddenly becoming a Patriots fan this season. But you can’t blame a person for being a LeBron fan, or suddenly watching U.S. Open matches because Serena Williams is playing.</p><p>The fact is, I wouldn’t watch Barcelona without #10. I don’t think Barcelona are my team. I’m not even sure I’m ready to pick a team, yet. So when I’m cheering for Barcelona goals in the Champions League, it’s not because I want Barca to win the trophy. It’s because I want Messi to win the trophy. Again.</p><p>There’s little point in writing about what he does. He scores. All of the time, in every way possible. It’s better to watch it. That’s what I do. But he also does the kinds of things that make writers want to write. He causes moments, experiences.</p><h2>Hat Trick</h2><p>Let’s reflect on Messi’s 2019 hat trick away at Real Betis.</p><p>It started with a now-signature Messi free kick. And it ended with something I’d never seen before. Again, I’ve watched only a few seasons of international soccer in my life. But when he floated that ball over the keeper’s hands and banked it off the crossbar like it was a bumper at a bowling alley, I heard the same feeling in the commentators’ voices.</p><p>I didn’t even recognize it as a chip shot when it went in. Honestly, I couldn’t figure out exactly what <em>had</em> happened. The ball came back to Messi after he’d passed it away and then it mysteriously changed directions off his foot. I thought it was a cross. Or a mistake. And then it slowly arced over the keeper—who obviously was not able to calculate such an angle to prepare for a shot—and the stadium was delirious.</p><p><em>What in the world was that?</em></p><p>It was like an optical illusion—like, in FIFA, when you miss an easy shot or run your defensive player straight past an oncoming attacker because of the sideways TV camera perspective.</p><p>That kind of thing—it’s a unique moment. Here are a couple of veteran commentators who’ve probably been calling games for a decade or two, who have certainly been following the sport since they were kids, watching a guy who scores in almost every game do the same thing he always does. But he gets them anyway. He does it a little differently, in a way that’s just a bit closer to impossible, and instantly they’re at the same viewing angle as me. All of the context of the game, all of the legends and traditions and statistics and patterns drop away in a moment like that and leave nothing but the naked shock of witnessing a <em>new thing</em>.</p><p>We had shared in an experience of sublimity. It doesn’t take a career in journalism to appreciate it; the <a href="https://youtu.be/zSVUE9tFAOc">French guys said it best</a>. It was pure, a snapshot with as much power as a decades-long rivalry full of legends. It was like a black hole: Barcelona could have lost that game but the result would have been sucked through the event horizon of that goal. It was the definition of an instant classic.</p><p>A moment like that also voids any claims of bandwagon-jumping. Barca fan or not, you have to love it. Its beauty was a universal truth. Ask the <a href="https://youtu.be/CkEaV3WDavY?t=43">away fans</a>.</p><h2>Lucky</h2><p>That goal is why I’m lucky I fell in love with soccer when I did. I might’ve missed Messi’s 70-goal season and his Champions League trophies. But I’ll still see enjoy experiences like his Betis hat trick and his free kick against Liverpool as long as he decides to lace up. People can argue about the greatness of Pele, Ronaldinho, Zidane and make spreadsheets comparing the stats and weighing the trophies. It doesn’t matter, in the end. I’m watching now, and I’m seeing unimaginable things happening at the feet of Lionel Messi. That brings me joy.</p><hr><ol><li><span id="1-f">I didn’t know, then, that Freddy Adu scored his debut goal in the MLS when he was 14. 14! And it’s nice to see that he’s still playing.</span> <a href="#1">⤴️</a></li></ol>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>